Since we will look into whether 2 or more
concurrent threads are correctly handling
shared variables, let's introduce a system
model for the critical section problem.
From now on, we assume each of
our threads looks like this:
we have a loop that runs forever (it's a
model, of course it will stop in practice,
but from the model perspective we do not
assume anything about when it will stop)
inside the loop, we have a critical section,
the one in which we read/write shared variables,
we assume shared variables are accessed with
atomic read/write operations, so only one read
or write operation can be performed at a time
before the critical section, we have an entry
section, a statement/line/multiple lines whose
execution implies the critical section can start:
you can see the entry section as the portion in
which the thread is trying to acquire a LOCK,
its right to enter its critical section
after the critical section, we have an exit
section, a statement/line/multiple lines whose
execution implies the critical section is over:
you can see the exit section as the portion
in which the thread releases its LOCK,
for someone else to enter their critical section
and a remainder section, basically the rest
of the code in which we do not worry
about reading/writing shared variables.
Notice that for simplicity we also
assume threads' execution does not fail!
Our goal of having 2 or more
concurrent threads correctly handling
shared variables can then be formulated as:
Define an entry and an exit section that ensure:
Mutual exclusion,
Progress (i.e., no deadlock/no livelock), and
Fairness (e.g., bounded waiting or no starvation).
Mutual exclusion means that only one thread
at a time can execute its critical section.
Progress means that if no thread
is in its critical section and one
is/some are trying to enter their, then one
must enter its critical section in bounded time.
Notice that we do not make any assumption about
the duration of the reminder section of
a thread. A thread can stay there for
as long as it needs. The duration of the
reminder section is NOT bounded in time.
Let's put also a temporary extra assumption
for now: we only have 2 concurrent threads.
If we want to visualize such
behavior it looks like this figure.
As you can see, only one thread
at a time can enter the critical
region. If a thread B tries to enter it when
another thread A is in it, then B waits.
What we are going to do next is to look
at various ways of defining the entry
and exit section and ask ourselves: does solution
X ensure mutual exclusion, progress, and fairness?
We want formal correctness proofs. We cannot
answer with "it looks like it does!" nor with
"I tried running the code 1000000 times and
it never broke, so I am confident it does".
To provide a formal answer, we are going to
try to find one execution of the threads that
breaks one of the properties. If we find it, then
the solution is not valid (it breaks one of the
desired properties). If we show such an execution
does not exist, then the solution is valid.
Let's try to look at a specific (simple)
example, which we refer to as check-completion.
Let's say the code of our 2
threads, A and B, looks like this.
They both share 2 boolean
variables, flagA and flagB,
initially set to false, which they use to indicate
their intention to enter the critical section.
Here I show A's code. B's code is symmetric.
In its entry section, A waits as long
as B's flag is true in a while loop.
This is called busywait because A is
using CPU cycles to spin in a loop.
The loop ends when B sets its flag to false.
After that, A sets its flag to true,
enters the critical section, and when the
critical section is over sets its flag to false.
Is this solution to the critical
section problem valid or not?
I strongly suggest you stop the video and
try to reason and provide a formal answer.
Now let's try to answer the question together.
That is, let's try to find an example
showing one of the properties can be violated.
Can the property of mutual exclusion be violated?
For instance, can A enter its critical
section while B is in its critical section?
Let's answer the question
with the help of this drawing.
In this drawing, we see that A
enters its critical section after B
entered its own but before B
exited it. Can this happen?.
To happen, sometime before entering its
critical section A needs to set its flag
to true (that's what the code says).
And before that, A needs to see that
the value of flagB is false to exit the busywait
while loop (again, that's what the code says).
Now let's focus on B. To enter its
critical section, B needs to set
flagB to true (that's what the code says).
Now we are at a critical point. In our example, if
we assume B sets its flagB to true before A sees
flagB's value is false, then it means in between
these two events B completes its critical section,
otherwise A cannot see flagB being false...
In the example we are studying, the point
in which B sets flagB to true comes after
A sees flagB value to be false.
So now we are left with one question: can B
see flagA being false in between the time A
sees flagB to be false and B sets flagB to true?
The answer is yes because flagA is
initially set to false and is also set to
false every time A exits its critical section.
So, in the figure, the portion of time during
which A has not yet entered its critical section
is a period during which flagA's value is false.
We have found an example that breaks the
mutual exclusion, which implies the code
is NOT a solution to the critical section problem.
Once you listen to this argumentation,
you "digest" it and you understand it,
you will probably agree that proving whether a
solution to the critical problem is valid or not
is very challenging. In all the following
videos, I strongly suggest you stop
and try to formally find out yourself
whether a solution is correct or not!